All right. All right. Well, good evening
everybody. It's six o'clock, so I'm
going to call the uh meeting of
committees to order. Um Mr. Harris,
we're going to start with a roll call of
members and then I'll have some
reminders and announcements at the top
of the meeting. Mr. Harris,
here. Mr. Roy,
Mr. Here, Mr. Smith here, Miss here, Mr.
here, present here. Uh, council Royo is
excused this evening. Okay. So, a few
reminders and announcements for council
and everyone here's with us. So, please
take a moment to silence your phones and
your devices if you haven't done so
already. This meeting and its
participants are being recorded. Uh, so
tonight we have meetings of committees
of council. Uh, just be advised there is
no general public comment periods during
this meeting. However, committee chairs
may call for comments uh from the public
for legislative items, which are bills
and resolutions. Comment uh if there are
any are limited to three minutes per
speaker, and please begin with your name
and block of residence for our uh
meeting minutes. As you may have
noticed, counselors and attendees, uh we
have returned to using our committee
meeting table. This is an effort to make
a distinction between this type of
meeting and our regular meeting, bring
us closer and also encourage more
discussion between members of council,
which is difficult to do on a day when
we're all trying to look around each
other. Um, so a couple of notes about
that. Um, the speakers in front of us
will allow us to be heard on the live
stream and we've asked our audience to
sit in the first two rows so we can be
heard in the room. Um, please do speak
up, but you don't need to yell
counselors. That's okay.
Um, anyone who's making public comment
tonight, if it's called for, can simply
stand and do it from their seat. And any
presenters will be asked to come up to
the table this evening and join us. So,
all right. And thank you for um uh
helping us and bearing with us as we
work on this new slash old format for
this meeting. All right. Uh, councilors,
the first item tonight is the approval
of the May 5th, 2025 committee meeting
minutes. I'll hear a motion on those.
Motion to approve. Second. Have a motion
and a second. Are there any council
comments on the meeting minutes?
All right. Hearing none. Mr. Harris, if
you call the role on this one.
Mr. M. I. Mr. Please. I. M. I. Miss
Stevens. I. Mr. H. I. President.
I. Great. That'll take us to the
committee of the whole which we're doing
at the head of the meeting tonight. Uh
the first item is our ethics commission
and applicant interviews. So we will
hold our final interviews for applicants
to the ethic commission this evening. As
a reminder, we heard from our first
nominee at our last meeting. Applicants
were chosen for interviews by rank
choice voting system. Uh thank you to
all of you. Um and originally interviews
were held for the top four vote getters,
but there was a tie, so there will be
five total. We'll have four this
evening. Uh we will not be voting this
evening. As a reminder, motions to
nominate will be heard at our June 10th
regular meeting of council. And
applicants, you're not required to
attend that meeting, but you're of
course welcome to. Um, so for our
applicants, I'll have you come up and
have a seat and join us. Um, I'll ask
you to affirm questions that you've
already affirmed, uh, but do so for the
meeting record. Um, and then uh you'll
have a minute to introduce yourself,
talk about why you'd like to serve, and
then there'll be time for questions from
council. And as we did at our last
meeting, counselors, uh we'll just go
around and we can ask a question uh or
and a follow-up if we'd like of of the
applicant. So, uh we'll begin with uh
Mr. Paul Culra who's here this evening.
Hold on. Please come on
up. if you could have a seat right next
to council Diaz there. Thank you for
joining us tonight.
Thank you for being here. All right, Mr.
Coburn, I'm going to ask you to affirm
those questions. Uh so first, is your
primary residence located within the
city of Lancaster? Yes. Thank you. Have
uh you held any appointed or elected
office within the city government within
the last year? No, I haven't. Have you
held any political party office within
the last year? No, I haven't. And have
you held any political action committee
positions within the last year? No, I
haven't. Thank you so much. Um, if you
would take a minute to please introduce
yourself and tell us why you are
interested in this commission. Um,
again, my name is Paul Cobbrath, uh,
Lancaster resident, lifelong Lancaster
resident.
um born and raised uh graduated from
Casy High School, couple years of
college, a couple degrees in college,
masters in human services and a masters
in social work. Uh I spent my first
probably 20 years with the Boys and
Girls Club of Lancaster as the
operations director. Uh then I moved on
to uh children and youth and spent the
next few several years there as the
uh supervisor in the child neglect unit.
Uh at that time I was tapped to take
over the Urban League of Lancaster as
the president and CEO. Uh which I've
held that position for about five years
before moving
on. And uh I ended up at Daddy Stevens
College where I end I was the director
of uh multicultural affairs, student
engagement and student retention.
Uh it's where I uh retired from. I
actually retired from there.
Um, I'm currently the president of the
uh local branch of the National Action
Network uh which is the social uh
service organization that that uh
targets uh issues dealing with uh
quality of life issues here in Lancaster
City for our community residents. Thank
you so much. Appreciate that. Um I'm
going to just go around to members of
council uh for your questions. Um, as a
reminder, you all submitted some
questions, so I just aggregated them in
the list and you can choose to use them
if you wish or you could ask a different
one. Uh, council Diaz, we'll just go
right around. We'll we'll begin with
you. How do you see yourself holding
accountability to the checks and balance
needed for the city and fairness to the
residents?
uh in many of my positions uh I've u
held those types of responsibilities
uh especially uh in the area uh with
uh issues with the city issues with the
college issues with community residents.
Um, so, uh, I have, I think, a a strong
background ground in in, uh, uh,
holding,
uh, people, organizations, and entities
accountable.
Thank you, Council H. Thank you, Paul,
for joining us. Um, how do you kind of
ensure that your personal beliefs um or
biases maybe don't affect necessarily a
situation where you're called to be an
impartial arbiter or um mediator?
How do you how do you ensure that Yeah,
just shoot me. I have artillery ears.
So, no worries. Sorry about that. Um,
how do you ensure that your uh personal
beliefs don't necessarily conflict with
your responsibility to be an impartial
uh uh arbiter or mediator?
Um, how do how would I really not
understanding your question? Just asking
like how do you make sure that your
personal beliefs or biases don't get in
the way of being neutral? Okay, that was
Sorry, that's a little more concise.
Um during my tenure at at that Stevens,
I uh uh uh ran and and orchestrated or
organized the
uh a a program where we had to
uh bring a lot of folks in for to check
out their ability to be biased in some
of the decision making uh pertain to the
college itself, its programs, students
and things like that. Uh I myself, you
know, had to make sure that my biases
didn't impact any of my decisions. Uh
and I'm I'm pretty comfortable with uh
uh of of separating myself from the
issue at hand, my biases and feelings
and things of that nature to the issue
at hand and deal with only the facts.
Thank you. Thank you. I'll go I'll just
help couple as we go around. Uh Mr.
Cobra, thank you again for being here
tonight. This is of course a volunteer
position. Um have you ever served on any
other volunteer boards or commissions?
And what did you learn from that
experience? I served uh I did a stint
here in in Lanster as the on the human
relations comm uh commission. I think I
served probably about one term on there.
I think that was during
I would date myself
but it's okay. It was early and uh you
know uh I uh was introduced to a lot of
the uh things that will be impacting the
city uh and some of the things that the
ethics committee will be dealing
with. Thank you.
Uh thank you Mr. Colbert for being here
with us this evening. How do you believe
that integrity and honesty in elected
officials can build community engagement
and trust?
Uh that's it's paramount to to uh uh
building the trust especially with the
community uh if you don't have integrity
you know uh you can't really uh
accomplish anything. Uh the integrity
uh will lead
to you know
holding the city administration, city
folks and everybody accountable to uh to
the issues at hand or the ethical issues
that may be confronted by medicine.
Thank you.
Thank you madame president. Um good
evening Paul. Thank you for your
willingness to serve. Uh how will you
ensure that your
decisions are consistent across cases
within the commission regardless of a
person's political power or connections?
Uh well, I think you have to really be
comfortable with uh your ability to
understand the issues and to really
analyze the issue and then like you said
uh make sure that your your personal
opinions and
but also proactively guide city
officials uh on how to make good
decisions that reflect the values of
justice, diversity, transparency, and
community benefit.
uh considering both the intended and
unintended impacts of the decisions we
make um and the desires um that our
residents have for their communities. So
that's what really brings me uh here to
this table.
Thank you so much. I'll be at that. So,
how do you see yourself holding
accountability to checks and balance
needed for the city and the fairness of
to the residents?
Good question. Um, I think, uh, when it
comes to accountability, especially
through an ethics commission, uh, it
really comes through transparency, uh,
and making sure that the ethics
commission is transparent in the work it
does. um whether it is reporting at a
city council or publishing their
findings um for the public to see. Um so
when it comes to accountability um our
role as the ethics commission is to
review and report. Um it is up to the
city and how they would like to
um decide to punish as far up to um
charges if need be.
So that's how that
would counselor hir. Uh thank you,
Grant. Um I couldn't help but notice uh
in reviewing your application your uh
and you mentioned your human resources
um background and so I can imagine that
you've probably come across a situation
where you have handled an ethics
complaint. Um can you talk about how you
approach that and and how you'd handle
that situation? Yeah, usually um ethics
complaints or complaints in general um
are met with
investigatory powers of HR. Um so often
um it is interviewing firsthand uh
people who have you know are impacted um
getting their sides of the story um
getting any third party witnesses um and
then ultimately coming to a decision
whether it is as a team uh HR team or
looking for other um players other city
officials to um advise on whether good
practices were were um followed um and
then ultimately coming up with a
decision on what action plan will be put
in place for that e ethics infraction.
Thank you. Thank
you. Can you tell us about any other
volunteer positions you've held on
boards or commissions? What were they
and what was something you learned by
doing that? Yes, currently I serve on
the personnel committee of the ODC or
Occupational Development Center of
Lancaster. Um, I've learned a lot from
them. Um, I've learned that running a
small nonprofit is not easy. Uh, and
that you really do have to uh work with
the community um to
build your your base, your um resources
um in order to survive.
This is true. Yeah,
thank you so much, Councelor M. Thank
you, Council President. Thank you for
being here this evening. Thank you. How
do you believe that integrity and
honesty and elected officials can help
build trust and engagement in the
community? Yeah. Um, integrity, um, I
think people like to think of it as, you
know, making the right decision when
nobody's looking. Um and I think that
the ethical code of conduct or an
ethical framework would help um develop
trust uh with the community uh knowing
that there is guidelines for decision
making in the city that um put the
community at the center. Um so when
integrity is mentioned um I think when
we hold our city officials and myself um
to integrity I think it comes down to is
when nobody's watching across the table
inside the committee meetings are we
treating each other with respect um have
similar goals towards justice truth and
ultimately community benefit.
Thank you. You're
welcome. Thank you, Madam President, and
thank you for being here tonight. How
will you ensure that your decisions
across your decisions are consistent
across cases within the commission
regardless of a person's political power
or connections? Oh, yeah. I think uh it
comes from listening. Um and ultimately
we are a bunch of people with different
opinions in a room. Um if it ever came
to the point of needing to recuse
myself, u I would do that. Um but
listening to different opinions um I
think is imperative to coming to a
consensus. Thank you.
Good evening. Good evening. Could you
tell us about a time when we had an
ethical dilemma and how you solved it?
Absolutely. Um so in a former position
that I held uh I did hold uh a POA um
with the IRS. Um and once that position
was done um ethically I had a
responsibility to end that POA and no
longer represent the company. Um so in
that regard that ethics
um dilemma was resolved. Um I think
there's other ethics dilemmas that I've
noticed. Um, one that particularly,
um, is recent, um, one that shows that
residents aren't being prioritized, um,
in our city, and that comes with the
residential permanent parking program.
We are in a crisis parking crisis. Um,
and as the city committed to reviewing
our residential permit parking program,
um, we might not see any changes until
2026. Meanwhile, the parking authority
has committed to continued um ticketing
um and now continued ticketing via
cameras. Um so, putting that ethical
framework into the lens is it okay to
uh what's it called? Find before we fix
is the saying that I put in place. So,
that's kind of like a an example of how
an ethical framework would guide
decision- making here and now.
Thank you. Thank you very much,
counselors. Any additional questions?
Thank you. Thank you for joining us.
Thank you. Thank you.
And last but not least, we have
Christopher
Souls. Christopher, you're the first one
here and you're the last one to
interview, but I was going
alphabetically, so I apologize for that.
Okay, I'm going to have you affirm these
questions. Uh, is your primary residence
within the city of Lancaster? Yes. Uh,
have you held any appointed or elected
office within the city government within
the last year? I have not. Have you held
any political party office within the
last year? Have not. Have you held any
political action committee position
within the last year? I have not.
Bless you. All right. I'm going to give
you a minute to introduce yourself and
talk about why you'd like to serve.
Great. Uh, mayor, Madam President,
council members, I'm really honored to
be here. I've also really enjoyed
hearing um the interviews of the other
candidates. Um, I my name is Chris Salt.
Um, I was born and raised in Vermont.
Um, actually grew up in Burlington,
Vermont. Um, which I'll get back to next
very quickly. Um, then I moved to
Cleveland, Ohio, and I lived in the
inner city there for about 27 years. And
then my wife and I moved here in 2018,
and we love it here. We're never moving.
Um, love this place dearly. I worked for
um, an organization called 10,000
villages, which is just 20 minutes north
of here, uh, starting in 2006. And I
traveled to the city often, and so I got
to know the city for about 20 last 20
years and fell in love with it. So I
kind of, uh, feel like this is kind of
my kind of new adopted home. Um, yeah.
So I've worked in the fair trade world
for about 20 years. and I saw somebody
sent me this opportunity and I was like,
"Oh, I see a lot of what I've devoted my
career to in this position." Um, I think
that what you all do um in public
service is uh I think a very special
kind of calling. It also has a special
responsibility which I think is
something that should be shared with the
community. Um, so I think that's a
really um interesting new opportunity
for the city to um to help I'd say be a
better city. Thank you so much. Hey,
Council
Diaz. Thank you for coming. Um, how do
you see yourself holding accountability
to the checks and balance needed for the
city and fairness to our residents?
Yeah. Um well, as you could probably
tell, like being in the fair trade
world, the fairness is something that is
something as very passionate uh I'm very
passionate about. Um and uh kind of
interestingly um in my organization now,
we have a code of practice that we hold
200 uh small businesses to the United
States and Canada. They've agreed to
behave a certain way and they've asked
us to hold them accountable. So I'm very
familiar with that kind of dance, right?
It's a very important one to make. Um I
think that within um a group having lots
of diverse opinions that's all very
great and building community within that
group is important but to understand the
letter of the law right and the rule of
law that we have agreed to work with
right so I think being very mindful and
building a lot of understanding with
what are the what are the tools that we
are actually using to to work rather
than like my own personal opinion about
a policy or something that impacts me as
a resident. I think continuously
grounding ourselves in the basis of the
ethics act which is passed by the you
know Pennsylvania legislature.
Thank you councelor Hirs. Uh thank you
Chris for being here. Um I was going to
ask how your personal beliefs uh how do
you avoid them interfering with your
decision-m? You kind of just spoke to
that. Um, so I'll ask uh, you know, how
would you handle a situation where you
know someone was um, the subject of an
ethics complaint?
Would I would if I knew them? Yes. If
you if they were a colleague, if they
were someone you worked with. Yeah.
Yeah. Obviously, it depends on certainly
the context and situation. Of course. Um
but for the sake of this this question
I'd say um once understood the the the
context of that situation then you know
first I would probably want to recuse
myself if that if that was you know I
would automatically offer that um if
that would help the situation come to
some better resolution.
Um being able to understand the um the
hat that you wear per se is really
important in uh any kind of ethics work
that you would do and knowing that if my
presence as an individual would then
undermine the successful outcome of that
is very very important to understand. Um
it's it's challenging obviously and kind
of messy but I think that my my first
inclination would be to you know if I
like knew somebody and they were part of
it that I would recuse myself.
Thank you.
Can you tell us about any uh volunteer
boards or commissions you've served on
in the past? What were they and what did
you learn from that experience? Yeah. Um
so I've served on when I lived in
Cleveland, I was part of a little um a
housing cooperative and I was the vice
president and treasurer of that
organization for about seven years. I
was the several positions on uh the Heso
Neighborhood Association, historic
preservation, new community development
organization in Cleveland. That was
probably about 10 years. Um and I'm I'm
currently the vice president of the
World Fair Trade Organization. I'm in my
second term. I was elected in September
of 2019 in Lima, Peru by this global um
group of fair trade enterprises around
the world. I served one term which was
extended. It was a four-year term. It
was extended five year to one year,
excuse me, two five years from four
years because of the pandemic and then
was just reelected last September in
Cape Town, South Africa to another term
and then was internally elected to be
the vice president. That's all
volunteer. Um and also I've worked uh my
10 years with 10,000 villages I did a
lot of nonprofit board development as
well across the United States and in
Canada. And um yeah, so there there's a
couple others, but that's kind of the
the bulk of it.
Thank you so much for sharing that,
Council Amed. Thank you, Council
President, and thank you for being here
this evening, sir. How do you believe
that integrity and honesty in elected
officials can build trust and engagement
within the community? Yeah, but um
someone else just mentioned our current
um political dialogue and and um you
know the tone right now is is really
stark. I think that in Lancaster City um
especially we have an opportunity to
control what we have going in our
community. The integrity and trust that
you all have and and Lancaster elected
officials have with the residents is the
currency by which you are able to spend
the trust of the residents and the you
know that you're supposed to represent
their interests. And if that's you know
if that's seen as somehow damaged or
somehow tainted in some way then it
doesn't allow you to fully represent all
the residents in the city to make the
best community possible. I mean, it's
really the biggest issue, right?
Thank you, Council Cle. Thank you,
councelor President. Thank you for being
here tonight. And uh how will you ensure
that your decisions are consistently
worse cases within the commission
regardless of a person's political power
or connections? Yeah, it's such a great
question and it's also a very very
difficult one to ensure um but is the
right question to be asking. Um I think
certainly from my own um individual
standpoint um being very very mindful
about my own presentation and my own
power and privilege and white male you
know old I've got gray beard here you
know English- speakaking US password I
have a whole list of things that have
some type of power and privilege
associated to them and being mindful
about what that represents to people is
really important. also all of the
individuals um within you know the
ethics commission would also be very
very important to understand as well and
then in all of the individuals involved
in a specific case are also really
important to understand
then you know we can have our own
opinions we can have our own thoughts
we're all human but like the code is the
code right so like that is what we we go
by we can discuss all of our opinion
opinions about things and the way we
appeal or emotions or whatever. We're
humans. That's relevant in that
conversation. But any action needs to be
cited by right by the um ethics act,
right? So there's it's important to to
vent and have those discussions and
community and collaboration. Um and also
making sure that
everyone no matter their power and
privilege has an a way to be heard and
listened and
respected. But the law is law, right? So
that I think is is what will drive
everything. Thank you. Thank you.
Hello. Hello. Could you tell us about a
time when you had enough of the money
and how you solved it? Oh my goodness. I
have so many and that I could share
publicly. Um yeah, so yeah, I've I've
been in HR and training for a long time.
So I have lots of of um examples where
there were was a a complaint, an ethics
complaint and then there was another um
a reaction to someone who was a part of
that. And often times you know those
conflicts which I have a lot of
experience unfortunately with conflict
management um that you know usually
those are misunderstandings. So like
being able to listen to people and have
them be heard and respected and then
bringing them together to them
understand there's some issue here right
but there's also some misunderstanding
trying to build understanding um I'm
generalizing because I I don't want to
go into specific examples but that
that's usually how I approach those one
example that I can share is um I say
just in um so I'm executive director of
the fair trade federation and we have
like I said 200 businesses in the United
States and ADA, if you're at all
familiar with the fair trade movement,
it comes from a great place, right, to
wanting to do good to represent
marginalized producers and farmers
around the world. The way I was
introduced to it was Sally Stress and it
was so othering this experience where it
was like this white saviorism, you know,
you give, you know, a dollar a day, this
person, starving little kid in Ethiopia
can be have a slightly better life. And
that whole kind of like culture and
language of othering white saviorism and
and um heropreneurship as I like to call
it has been kind of the heart of that.
That's the kind of values pitch and it's
not right. Right. So like I kept
pointing this out to the organization
for many years like and finally got to a
place where I was like okay we need to
do something about this and like
decolonize the language that we're using
right so it doesn't other those people.
we're saying one thing and we've we've
we're we're telling this emotional
story, but what we're doing actually has
harm to other people. So, when I said,
"Okay, um I'm the like old white guy in
the room. I don't think this is right,
but we need to do something about this,
and um I probably am not the person to
be the face of this conversation." So I
recused myself from that whole
conversation and created a space for
people who um were really passionate
about the issue and they talked about it
and came up with uh we came up with a
Jedi commission justice equity diversity
inclusion and they were given a a charge
so to go through and decolonize a lot of
our language we kind of it's a slow
thing because it's a big you know kind
of cultural change. So that was one
thing where I I feel like I used my
power and privilege to kind of create a
space for others. Um where I saw like
like back to what I was saying earlier,
me being in that conversation probably
wouldn't be the best. I mean I would be
there if it was needed, but um there's
the optics of it as well. Um so that was
that was one thing. It was I know it's a
complicated ethical thing, but to me
that was something where I felt like I
needed to step away but help create the
space for that conversation to happen.
Thank you counselors. Any additional
questions?
Okay, Mr. Soul, thank you so much for
being here. For all of our applicants,
thank you again. Um again, we will uh
hear motions for appointment on our next
meeting at June 10th. There'll be a
place on the agenda for it. Um uh as a
reminder, we are um charged with
appointing three members to the ethics
commission. So um just keep that in mind
and we will hear more at our next
meeting. Thank you again. You're welcome
to stay or you can go. That's okay.
Thank you very much. We will continue uh
with committee of the whole. Our next
item is the administrative code
introduction. Uh Barry Hanburgger, city
solicitor is here this evening to talk
us through that.
And Mr. Hamburger, do you have a
presentation? I do. Okay. Mr. Harris,
does Mr. Harris have that? He does.
Okay, great.
Well, that's getting going. Those are
great interviews, all five of them. So,
we will have a very difficult decision.
Difficult choice.
And it's an intimidating. I mean,
there's six of us on one, so it's kind
of a lot. and it's a brand new thing.
So, all right, leave. Well, following up
on uh home rule topics, uh since you're
dealing with the ethics commission,
which is something created by the home
rule study commission and adopted
charter, um you also have an obligation
uh under the charter and the the home
rule law to adopt the administrative
code. and we have meetings scheduled
later to start introducing sections of
the code to you for consideration and
for your beginning to have discussions
uh and guidance towards those ends. Um
in order to help frame that for you, I
thought it would be helpful to have a
presentation to go a little bit over the
law that relates to it, the process that
the law requires, the process that your
study commission went through to frame
what you're going to see ultimately and
what you're ultimately going to have to
adopt. Um so as a as a little bit of
history and reminder um this council uh
by ordinance formed a government study
commission um to study the form of
government in the city of Lancaster.
That study commission um determined to
move from a thirdass city under the
optional charter law to a home rule
study to a home rule municipality and
crafted and proposed a charter. That
charter was submitted to the electors of
the city of Lancaster in November of
2024 and was um adopted. It became
effective on January 1st,
2025. The charter and the home rule
charter and optional plans law require
that council by ordinance and I want you
to keep that in mind. It's by ordinance.
There's a significant feature to this by
ordinance adopt an administrative code.
Mr.
So understanding a little bit about what
home rule does in terms of city
governance is very relevant to the
administrative code as a thirdass city
prior to adopting a home rule
charter. The city could only do what it
was specifically authorized by statute
or law to do. no power to do anything
that wasn't directed by the state
legislature. Home rule transfers the
authority to make those decisions to you
to the city to city council and the
city. Essentially, with home rule, you
can now do anything that state or
federal law does not prohibit. It's a
big difference. So if you were to take a
look at some of the operational codes in
the past, the third class city code and
the third class optional federal law
being the primary ones, Mr. Harris, you
could slip the next slide. Um they were
in large
part pieces of legislation that set
forth the authority to do things for the
city and absent that authority or absent
some other law that granted you
authority, you couldn't do anything.
They also set forth procedures by which
you would have to do certain of those
exercise certain of those powers. So not
only did the third class city code give
you the authority, but it set forth
procedures that you were required to
follow in order to exercise them that
were dictated by the state
legislature. You do not have to put in
the code, your powers. The powers, as we
said, are going to be determined by the
existence of existing law. What you do
have to do is draft an administrative
code that sets forth the procedures
you'll follow in exercising whatever
power you choose to
exercise. The administrative code is
adopted by ordinance and therefore it
can be amended by
ordinance. This is indeed the most
legislative flexibility a municipality
in Pennsylvania can have. It's very free
flowing. How long does it take you to
adopt an ordinance? You can do it. two
meetings generally, right? So, whatever
you adopt
here, you get to change if you want. If
times change, if the law changes, if
your operations change
and this is the single biggest change
from the way we've operated for decades,
which is everything had to be
specifically is set forth by a state
statute. It puts the most level of
self-governance that a Pennsylvania
municipality can have into your
hands. So, we move to the next slide
where they talk a little bit about what
the administrative code is mandated,
what you're mandated to have.
Um, the things that are going to be in
your administrative code are mandated
from two different sources. really
three, but the two the two mandate
sources are there some things that the
home rule and op home rule and optional
plans law requires and there there's
some things that your charter which your
electors your your voters elected and
adopted require you to include in the
administrative code. Five general
categories. Provisions for the exercise
of a control function for the management
of finances. Enumeration of the
departments, offices, authorities,
boards, commissions, and other
administrative units of the city
government. Their scope of
responsibility and internal procedures
for operation. budgeting, accounting and
financial policies, purchasing and
acquisition procedures, policies and
procedures governing personnel policies,
position descriptions, employee
recruitment, selection, orientation,
uh training, benefits, promotion, and
discharge. Um, other topics are will be
in the administrative code that weren't
mandated by uh the law include things
for example regarding forefeiter of
office. So, there's a provision in your
charter that mandates that city council
set forth the procedure to be followed
in order for an elected official to have
forfeited their office, be deemed to
forfeit their office. Uh there's other
similar things throughout that will be
throughout. Um in attempting to come to
a give you guys a starting point because
this will be your code. Um we've taken a
few items and sort of concepts and kept
them in mind as we are drafting. The
first is next slide. Yeah. And you can
select the next slide. Sorry. The first
is to be consistent with the terms and
spirit of the charter. That's obviously
the most significant, right? The charter
is now your Bible. That is the law of
the land. It is the single biggest law
underneath the Pennsylvania
Constitution.
That's what your electors have said is
the law. Any court's going to interpret
any ambiguity as against the chart. So
we obviously need to make sure that you
are consistent with not only the
specific language but the spirit.
Um assure internal controls and checks
and balances. This is to protect the
taxpayers. Continue current practices
where appropriate to assure that changes
made only were needed or desired. Assure
best practices.
Obviously the city wants to be the best
it can be and be directive only where
necessary and prudent. This is to
maintain your
flexibility. I take these principles and
I kind of summarize them in one phrase
which is sound governance. I mean if you
think about these five these are
principles that your administrative code
should set forth that assure that the
city is administered and governed in a
sound manner.
Uh, next
slide. So, what will the new code look
like? What's on the screen is the table
of contents from your current on the
lefth hand side from your current
codified ordinances.
Under the home rule charter law, our
charter has to be the various very first
item in the code. It's already been
placed there because remember became
effective January 1st.
The administrative code doesn't have to
repeat and really shouldn't repeat all
of the things in your 62page charter.
Your electors have already determined
many of the procedures that you're
mandated to follow and set them out very
clearly. We have in our current code of
ordinances a next section entitled
administrative legislation of which
there are a multitude of items.
Many of these will either be merged into
your administrative
code, moved out of this section because
they're really more general legislation
than they are administrative code and or
modified in terms of new language based
on the flexibility that you've now been
given um in terms of self-governance to
to and quite frankly updated. So, a lot
of these have been in place um decades
and decades. Um and this is uh a good
opportunity to even where there's no
real substantive change needed, some of
these have references that are outdated.
Um and so they will all be tweaked and
cleaned up and incorporated into this
part of it. What's below general
legislation? So, this is where your your
your big legislative ordinances lie,
right? So, your zoning ordinance, your
subdivision and land development
ordinance, your um building codes
ordinance, your property maintenance
ordinance, your storm water ordinance,
your sewer ordinance, your water
ordinance, your streets ordinance. All
of the big ordinances that we think of,
they're not getting touched. They're
still the law and they will continue to
be the law unless changed by ordinance
of city council. The only thing that's
getting worked on is the administrative
portions. And that's what the
administrative code is meant to cover.
Uh next
slide. So the next several slides are
and you notice the word draft because
you ultimately have to craft the
administrative code and what we've been
working on is to give you the starting
point. Um based on and and I'll just be
honest based on you know me being around
the city since 1994.
um my experience both in-house uh here
in the last 5 years and while serving as
outside counsel for the city of
Lancaster, an understanding of the law
and an understanding of of the things
that we think should be in here. In many
cases, you're not changing anything that
you're doing now. So, um in some cases,
we're making what is actually in writing
conform to what we do now, which is
always sometimes moved and changed
without change in ordinance and
legislation. Um but as we walk through
you'll see I mean obviously short title
and definition when we see some when you
see something here like powers and
division of powers organizational
structure department of officials those
are all things that are already covered
in your charter. This will not be a
repeat of the information. These are
where the study commission left places
for you as council to set forth
procedure and weigh in on how things
will be done. So these are the broad
categories but it's not a repeat of
what's in the charter. Um so you can see
here organizational structure remember I
mentioned earlier we have to lay out all
the departments and the organizational
that's mandated by the option by the
home rule charter law to be in the
charter even though we have it in other
places we need to put it in here and so
that is one place where there is a
little bit of a rinse and repeat from
the charter but that's because the law
requires us to do so. um you'll see
salaries of elected officials is is in
your charter, but what's left out of the
charter and on purpose from the study
commission was when and when you make
the changes. Are there any restrictions
on making the changes and how? So that's
what's going to be expanded upon by you
folks in the draft of your
administrative code.
um this section here, article five,
requirements of elected officials
regarding confidential information and
another section that has a similar title
but covers a broader sector of employees
as well. This is starting to be where
your ethics code might be part of it. It
could be standalone. It might be
inserted in these provisions. These
titles are placeholders for me uh and
the mayor in order to express places
where some of this language may appear.
Um next slide, please.
So again, if you recall, um your
administrative co administrative
ordinances section of your current code,
a lot of these topics that you see under
city council are already are are being
repeated. The reason being is again,
we're going to take that set of language
that's already there and we're going to
bring it current to your current
practices. There are some things that
need to be mandated in the code by the
charter. So for example, the charter
mandates that you meet twice a month,
right? So there are things that have to
be brought current uh as we do this. Um
again article 7 or ordinances and
resolutions. Um again there's things
left blank or unsaid in terms of some of
the specific procedures in terms of
ordinances and resolutions in the
administrative code. You have provisions
for that now and a lot of those are
going to be merged right into here. Um
uh I mentioned earlier there's a new
provision required by the charter
regarding forefeiter of offices uh of
office of elected officials. So this is
a section you will not have seen or even
had any any sight to see right uh
anywhere before. Um and you can slip
slip to the next slide burner please.
Um so uh you know when we get to boards
commissions and authorities again
there's some new methodologies and
requirements in the charter for how
members are appointed. This is laying
out a little bit more uh detail. It will
also do something that's necessary which
is to confirm that current board members
terms will continue. Um one of the sort
of oddities of the laws by adopting a
new charter. We've already done it with
your charter but we need to do it again
with the administrative code.
Um there'll be things like training
trainings are covered in here which is
not something that currently exists but
something that we're proposing and you
already have in practice. Uh so again
being merged into the code itself rather
than as a resolution which is what we
currently have. Um article 10 conflicts
of interest and disclosure of
confidential information. Again this is
starting to get into some things that
might be in the ethics code. Um these
are sort of starting places and holding
places for that. Um we do need to have a
section on budgets. So that's what
article 11 covers. Um, and what we've
done here, what we're proposing to do
here is you have very detailed budget
sections of your charter. I was going to
say there's a lot of but what we're
doing here is is again expanding on it.
We're bringing the calendars into the
administrative code, making them a
little bit more less wordy and more
tabular so they're followable. Um,
again, so this is for transparency too,
right? So anybody looking at our code
should be able to understand when the
budgets are going to be presented in the
process. Um hopefully this will this is
a starting point for you to discuss how
to do that. Um we need to have a section
on finance uh and accounting and that's
article 12 or at least the proposed
article 12 and you know we have to have
the city to have the ability to have
bank accounts. So this and these are all
things in your charter. You can slip the
slide switch slides. Um but the types of
things up here are things that we all do
but we don't think about the procedure.
They're all authorized by the charter
but now we're setting forth the
procedure. So how do we you know what
sort of fund policy should we have? What
sort of investment policy should we
have? What sort of borrowing policy
should we have? Um how do we process
transactions? All that was all those
were things covered in some part and
sometimes not by the third class city
code. Um obviously article 13
procurement disposal of city property.
Insurance and bonding is dealing with
several significant insurance issues
which we just want to make sure are
covered. Um, a new article here is
records and record retention, which is,
um, an article intended to make sure
that we're compliant with the state
record retention law. Um, which I know
is an issue that's been before this
council in the in the recent months. Um,
next slide,
please. Um, article 16 will have a lot
whole lot more sections than one and
two. The main reason is that employment
guidelines is going to be broken down
into a whole lot of subcategories. uh
that whole long list that I spoke about
earlier would be included in there. Keep
in mind that the administrative code
does not need to lay out every
procedure. It needs to lay out how
procedures will be created as well. So
there there will be things here that are
directing how policies are enacted and
and if they're enacted and they affect
for example the citizens and residents,
how do people know about them? Um so
when you get to the general provisions
which skipping civil service for a
second, you'll see uh publicly
accessible websites. So there's some
going to be some requirements that we're
buil we're suggesting be built in here
about what has to be on that website,
how it's used, how it's maintained to
asssure that residents and taxpayers and
others that are interested have good,
clear, and up-to-date information
regarding um city affairs. Obviously,
article 17, civil service, that is a law
that predates many of the laws and is
mandated on us. So the civil service
provisions which we already have in our
um existing codes will be brought here
into article
17. Uh next slide.
So how we how we I've uh how this is
starting for you. This is just the start
but um four four meetings work sessions
of the committee of the whole have been
scheduled. Um one a couple weeks from
now uh one in July, one in August, one
in September. Um the plan uh if I can
meet all the drafting needs
um is to to present about half of this
um on June 17th um and work through that
on the 17th and the 15th with still
ability obviously to carry on with more
discussions um and then present the
second half for discussion on August
19th for suggest for for discussion on
August 19th and September 16th. One of
the key components to this obviously is
what happens with your ethics code which
you're ultimately responsible for
drafting but you can't draft it without
input from the ethics commission. So
this this schedule is in large part um
determined controlled to some extent by
uh how fast we can get your ethics
commission uh up and running and giving
you the guidance it needs to draft that
first version of an ethics coup. which
is why it will be in the second phase of
the work, not what's presented obviously
on June 17. Sure. Um, next slide,
B. So, next steps.
Um, council action. Well, you've already
got one you're starting with, which is
completion of the ethics commission
appointments.
Um, review a draft of the administrative
code and complete transition. um really
to complete the transition from third
class cities to home rule is to adopt
this administrative code ordinance. One
thing that's not on here and and I and I
I'll say it. I think it's probably um
logical, but I really do think um before
the meeting on the 17th, I would I would
highly recommend that council members
spend a good deal of
time really looking at the charter and
reading its language repeatedly, really
digging into it because it's what's
going to control this. And if you don't
have a good understanding of what's in
the charter, it's going to make this a
harder process for you. Um, by
understanding the charter really well,
you'll see immediately when these come
to you where we've where we we are
expanding on what the charter to asked
us to expand on and where the sort of
the impetus is coming from.
Um, your questions and guidance are
vitally important throughout this
process. Th this will be your code. Um
it is the city's code. Um it is every
city council's code. And the beautiful
thing about it is it can be changed
as environment in this in the in the
country changes as law changes as the
city adapts as you adapt.
Um from a just a personal note
um you know I I started practicing with
the city in
1994. Um, to actually be part of this
and have the opportunity to to hand this
to you and let you do what you need to
do with it is a real big honor for me.
Um, it's it's something that is a living
breathing document
that I take I take uh extremely
seriously about the provisions of sound
governance coming through it. Um the
city has fortunately in my opinion been
soundly governed for many many years but
the code the third class city codes have
restricted it from creative
thinking creative decision-m.
This is going to require council
members to
maintain sound governance and marry that
against critical and and unique thinking
and not subvert the process for well we
just want to you know do something that
no one's ever done before and the law
doesn't allow. This is this document to
guide you to make sure that you're
thinking through everything you need to
think over time. And so I look forward
to to meeting with you um each of those
four meetings to getting questions from
you and the public. I know we'll we'll
talk about a a a way to submit questions
so that we can get revised answers and
drafts and research throughout the
process. Um because it's going to be a
lot. I'll tell you that we're not done
drafting and we're at about the same
length as the charter um in small font,
11oint font, not the same size font as
what's in the charter. So there there's
quite a bit there, but again, a lot of
it shouldn't be real new. I mean,
there's a good portion of it that's
that's really not. We will try to pre
present information in a way that you
can understand where it's coming from,
where it's been changed, where
something's new. Uh, and hopefully this
will um be a process that we can get
done here over the next several months.
Can I really quick? Um, can I I want to
kind of go back to the idea of the work
session and and how those meetings will
go because this is going to be very
different than even a committee meeting
like we're sitting here. Although this
is kind of my first step in hoping bring
us together uh on those. Um these work
sessions will really be similar to the
home rule study commission's work in
that we we will be having discussion.
There will be time for questions, but
there's no action that's going to be
taken, no votes that are going to be
taken at these meetings. So, um, Barry,
you said, you know, make come prepared,
know the charter really, really well
because everyone will be asked to weigh
in on these things and and and kind of
bring your perspective. Um, and some of
it could be super easy and and it makes
sense to just simply carry things
forward. But there will be things we'll
need to make some decisions about, but
there's no voting when we make those
decisions because what we're doing is
putting it all together into one
administrative code that will be uh have
a first reading um to adopt it on
October 28th in that schedule before us
and then a second reading and a vote on
November 11th. So, the work sessions are
truly just that. they are places for
council to have discussion. So my hope
is that everyone will come really
prepared to do so and it is like I said
very different than um our regular
meeting uh as well. So just be prepared
for that. And if I could just add to
that, thank you council president. Um
you're not going to have days to review
the first trunch of this. We're going to
send it out to council and make it
public and Barry's going to do a walkth
through of the content and show you the
sections that are reflect major changes
uh and sections that are the
continuation of the way that we have
been doing things. All of it is up for
grabs, but we are we're going to try to
focus on the things that are of
significant change. Council will then
have sever several weeks, two weeks or
so, two and a half weeks to then submit
written questions as will the public.
Those written questions will be funneled
to the solicitor's office. Then uh he
will work on responding and doing
research and whatever else that is
necessary to respond to the inquiries,
draft alternative language for the
consideration of this body. And then at
the second meeting uh July 15th, we'll
review all the questions and comments
from council and the public for that
section, have further discussion. Uh and
then um where there's consensus, great.
And where there is still not consensus
and we may need to come back to that
that particular topic, we will figure
out a time frame for doing that. But we
kept this so that by the middle of
September, we kind of have given you all
have given the administration marching
orders in terms of like what where you
want to see final language. Then with a
sufficient enough time before the end of
October to actually see a revised and
somewhat final draft before adoption in
in potentially in November. So I just
want to explain the cadence of the
meetings because they are going to be
different. Um but you will have like the
homework for now is just read the
charter. The next batch of homework is
to read the draft and provide comment.
Um ask questions for clarity things like
that. Then discussion and then we repeat
that whole process for the second trunch
of uh content. Um, so and I think we
we've done our best to try to split the
content. It's not all going
to flow like one article after the other
because some things are still in draft
form. You know, some things we still
need like the ethics
um ethics code. Um, but that but we're
we're trying to like give you the things
that and a little bit of a balance of
like this is relatively easy, this is a
little bit more complicated rather than
putting like all the hard stuff into one
bucket. We're trying to navigate that so
that there's a a cadence where we can
kind of like the flywheel can start
moving because it is a lot. Um, but it's
not a lot that's changing, but there are
certain sections of course that are new
and that things are that are being added
to change.
And we hope that consensus will be easy
on a lot of them and to put some humor
into it. So for example, if you remember
one of the various service topics was
short title like normally this would be
called administrative code or city of
Lancaster administrative code or
administrative code of the city of
Lancaster. We would hope that like we
can get consensus on one of those fairly
quickly and easily. Right now there
going to be other things that clearly
require your input and that you're going
to have different opinions on. And
again, what we're attempting to do is
give you a starting point. This is not,
hey, you have to do this cuz this is
counselors. That's a and b, um, there
are lots of reasons that some of these
things may be changed or not changed.
So, it's it really is a starting point.
Um, it's going to be the most
significant in terms of length piece of
legislation this council has done uh
during the mayor's term. Um, and I can't
think of one longer in my time here. Um
and in some ways a lot of it is minutia
but a lot of the minutiae is really
important. So um that's why that's why
you know we ended this with you know
your your questions your guidance is
vitally important and counselors I think
the biggest one of the biggest takeaways
besides read the charter and get ready
for this is that and nothing that we're
doing is written on a stone tablet.
um just like today, we change pieces of
our existing administrative code often
by ordinance or resolution. So, we can
change these pieces um but we need to
get one in place. We have a ticking
clock in front of us and it's good work
to dive into, but it's not um not
something that can be never changed
again. Nothing here is ever written in
stone. The only thing that's really
written in stone is that you can't make
any significant changes to the structure
of government, right, within five years
without doing another going through the
same process we just went through,
right? That's that's written in stone,
right? That's uh what's in the charter
is written in stone, but everything else
is is written in pencil.
Great. Thank you so much. Anything else
that on that topic, counselors? Anything
to add? I have a question if I may.
For those that don't read English, will
there be translations
for this group here? No. For anything
that's going to be Well, I mean, I I I'd
have to ask the mayor whether the staff
will be able to translate drafts as
they're moving on. I can't answer. Yeah.
Let let me get back to you about that
because
um we are we we try very hard when we're
doing uh official business like this to
have a professional translator translate
the the concept like the concepts of
government which can sometimes not get
translated well in like a Google for
example.
Um but I'm not sure
that we're going to have the staff
capacity or the financial resources um
in our budget now to translate
iterations of this but translating at
the end
um yeah so let's talk about it because I
think that that's going to be a
challenge for us on the timeline that we
have to translate each section
inhouse there is software though that
can automatically translate yeah it's
just what we found with that counselor
Diaz not Google. Yeah, it it is some of
it is not it some some of it is not
translated as well as we would like if
someone were actually you know um
walking through it and talking about how
to explain this particular concept in a
different language. this just in case
anybody comes forward and says, "Why
hasn't this been translated?" I will
just direct them to you because you
would be the one that would be
responsible answering and being
transparent to them because I'm sure it
will come up. Yeah. And and obviously we
would be happy to uh if there are
specific sections that people are
particularly interested in, we we can
certainly work to address those
particular areas. But as it relates to a
100page document that's going to
continue to be revised multiple times,
I'm I just don't know that I know that
we do not have the budget line item for
translation that would support that.
Thank
you. Anything additional from council?
Thank you, Council President. Uh my only
question comment I guess would be more
of a comment is uh you know other than
reading and getting more familiar with
the charter how could we make sure that
this body stays on pace with these
meetings and not try to rewrite the
charter in a working session? Well, I
guess that's going to be hopefully uh
some guidance from me um and being able
to point you to where the charter
already controls something.
Um and then just to focus as a group on
um where the goal line is, right? So
like we may have to you may have to make
some concessions to the shortness of
time at various points where like okay,
we've deliberated this for an hour on
the point of the name of the code. Um I
think we need to move forward. Um, and I
think I think I think I think as a group
you guys will be able to do that. I'm
I'm um I'm And in terms of the timing,
I'm more concerned ultimately just with
um the ethics part of it and that has a
that has an absolute 12-month deadline.
Um and for me, getting them done
together makes the most sense. Trying to
do the admin code after the ethics code
um is is challenging. Uh even though
legally we have six months longer for
this
um that being said that to me is the
biggest challenge to the time frame is
ethics code's got to get appointed uh
and then we need to get them convened
with a meeting to give some feedback um
and ideas and that's going to take more
than one meeting. I mean they're not
going to be able to come up in one
meeting. Um the study commission
fortunately did a whole lot of work on
ethics commissions and we have a whole
lot of information assembled by the
study commission um Pennsylvania economy
league that uh was guiding them that we
can give to the ethics commission to get
them started to give us the feedback
necessary to get started on an admin
code on an ethics code provision that
you ultimately are still responsible
for. Their job is to give you
preliminary input. Your job is to then
draft and adopt.
And I would I mean this is also for your
discussion as a working group. I mean if
you guys want to create a little bit of
uh you know um how you want to work
together you know that you uh you check
in after 15 minutes of discussion and
decide you know like is there consensus
around this? Do we need to move on? Know
that there are some kind of agreed upon
ways that you want to carry this out.
um that you that basically if there if
it's presented and you know um Mr.
handburgers like okay does anybody have
any significant concerns and if there
aren't okay we're moving on just those
that kind of pace and then where there
are concerns and you know if it's only
one person that has concerns then that
person gets heard and then if there's
any other additional conversation about
it if not then you know we do have to go
with consensus but also everyone should
be heard so
you all can decide how you want to do
that I I would also say I would
encourage you to use the month in
between each meeting to you know
independently send questions over. I
mean obviously you can't deliberate by
emails in between but you can send
questions to me um that I can and you'll
have a question why did you do this or
why does it say that why doesn't it say
this those are the types of things that
we can certainly work to answer to keep
maybe the the work sessions moving a
little more uh fluidly because some of
those preliminary questions will have
already been answered and and I will say
maybe even if we could um have some uh
education to the public on the process
and the timeline line and if they could
also ask questions in between directly
to the administration so the meetings
aren't getting bogged down with you know
a question and answer session. Um I will
I will say that the work sessions
because they're not legislative won't
have general okay public comment the
questions and answers that we are
submitting can also be submitted by the
public. There will be general comment.
I'm sorry. Not specific comment is
really what I'm saying. General comment.
Yes. Similar to the home rule study
commission meetings, but for each
individual item that we're working on,
no. Um, so they will be able to use that
and there is going to be communication.
Yeah. looking talked about this a little
bit in preparing to the public about
what these sessions are, how they will
function and how they can ask questions
and you know the the drafts will be
available to them the same time that
they're available to us. So yeah and so
I think just for those of you just
related to home rule on the point of
public comment the work sessions
happened there was dialogue among all
the home rule commissioners and then at
the end they took public comment and the
public could comment on any aspect of
anything that was discussed or or even
not discussed as part of the the charter
but there there's not it doesn't require
each individual section to pause for
public comment it's one public comment
that was what I was mainly and the other
thing is passed by ordinance as a whole.
Yeah, you will be able to say if you
have a question instead of asking a
question during the public comment
section, submit your question. If you
have a comment, we have comments so that
you can sort of keep the public sessions
to opinions, comments, suggestions,
question and answer can be through the
process. And the point of of having that
gap in between the meetings is to have
time to gather the the answers to the
questions, find the resources that we're
looking for um and have them for the
next meeting so that we can answer
questions, everybody's questions um with
some authority and not make a guess.
Well, and keep in mind that, you know, I
I I don't like to sort of like say I
need the time, but in reality, you're
doing a lot of new things and you're
under a new structure of government. Um,
and you may have a question that I
literally don't have the answer to. I
will have to research and research
doesn't happen in a day. We take some
time to make sure we give you the right
answers or the public the right answers
uh so that you're getting the right
guidance uh throughout the process and a
two-eek period to submit those questions
also so that the public and members of
council have time to formulate those
questions and Right.
Yeah.
Great. Anything else?
I was just going to ask real briefly,
um, is there any anything we've seen
from other cities that have undergone
this process that we should take note
of? Either things that have gone well,
things have not gone well. Well, uh, in
in reality, no. Um, because we're the
most recent city to do it in quite a
while. Um the other municipalities that
have converted to the home rule um one
have been different types of
municipalities have oftentimes come out
of act 47 um and had different uh
financial constraints and or different
issues. Um I will tell you that I've
looked at other administrative codes. Um
uh I've tried to to pick the parts that
were done well. I've relied on guidance
from Pennsylvania Economy League to
point out where um they thought uh admin
codes were particularly well done or
particularly not. Um but is there any
one model? No. And the answer reason is
because our charter is unique. It's
charter unto ourselves. It's not the
charter of Allentown. It's not the
charter of you know a particular burrow,
Mahanoi City for example. Um while all
of those may have some nice language and
concepts, they're not yours. They're
always different.
I try because I have a friend that she's
a city council person in Minnesota and
we talk back and forth about the charter
and she she goes, "Oh my god, your
charter is really crazy." And she would
give me her feedback. So, they're all
different.
Uh the the only um reference that we
would have to draft the administrative
code is the home rule or Yes. So to to
what extent uh the administrative code
must comply with state law. Well, it it
has to comply with the home rule charter
law. Uh it has to comply with our
charter. It's those five
enumerated topics that must be covered.
Um it can't be inconsistent with the
charter. So you can't say oh um for
example the best easiest example would
be the charter says you must meet twice
a month. Oh well we want to take you
know only do like we've been doing and
have one meeting in July and August
each. You can't do that. You can't write
a code. Yeah that does that. You have to
have a code that's consistent with the
charter. The charter is your enabling
authority. the I mean to to state law
again the charter the charter now as a
home rule municipality you can do
anything that's not prohibited by state
law okay so there isn't any state law
that's going to say this has to be in
your charter other than the five things
that I five topical areas that I covered
earlier and a few topics that are
specifically set forth in the charter
okay it's why this is a really
challenging process
uh is to try and figure out
a what do we want to do, b how should we
do it and then c how should we write it?
Um and
fortunately, you know, um the third
class city code in many cases is a
well-ritten document. Not all state
legislation is and parts of it I might
quibble with but in general it has we've
been operating in certain ways because
of it and some of those things are
incorporated here and because they are
best practices
and then there are areas where the
charter adopted essentially thirdass
city code practices. So again we have
some guidance in the form of a third
class city code but we're not limited by
it to the extent that it doesn't uh
conflict with the charter itself.
Thank you. You're welcome.
Anything else for the good of the order?
I thank you very much for giving us that
introduction. Thank you, council. Look
forward to diving in. I look forward to
seeing you again in June. Thank you.
Indeed.
Enjoyed. Okay. Yeah. So, council, you
have that uh
Yeah, the start of June. Again June, I
should say. You're right. Again. All
right. So, we'll continue with the
committee of the whole. Uh, this begins
uh resolutions that will need to be
introduced uh uh or moved out of
committee um if council wishes them to
be. We begin with council resolution 41.
That's uh recognizing im immigrant
heritage month and will refugee day. Uh
councelor men, you're introducing this
one. You'd like to share a little bit
about it? Uh yes. Um uh thank you
council president. Um uh this is an
annual resolution to uh recognize World
Refugee Day um and immigrant heritage
month which is June of uh 2025 and World
Refugee Day is on June 20th. Um and this
resolution uh is just going to honor and
recognize the contributions made by uh
both our immigrant community as well as
celebrating World Refugee Day here in
that concludes my report. Great. Thank
you so much for doing that. Um, and
councelor Med, uh, do you have a motion
on this one? I will move council
resolution number
412025 to our next meeting of full
council on the 10th. Second. Motion and
a second. Any council comments on the
resolution? Oh, I'm so sorry. Oh, this
is committee the whole. Sorry. I'm we're
we're doing it first, so we're all
backwards. Um, okay. Uh, all those in
favor of moving that to our next
meeting. I I any opposed?
Thank you very much. Um our next
resolution number 42 is recognizing
Junth. Councelor Craig, you are
introducing this one. If you have
anything to share with us. Um not
particularly. Um Junth is a
relatively new holiday for most
people, but um in the African-American
community, it has been recognized for a
very long time. And um I'm just pleased
that the city of Lancaster has has um
taken it upon themselves to recognize
Junth and and the history behind it.
Thank you very
much. And do you have a motion for this
one, Council? Sure do. A motion to
approve. Motion to move
to full council intent. Second. Any
additional council comments on it?
All in favor?
Any
opposed? Okay. Thank you so much. Uh our
next resolution is resolution number 43
recognizing Pride Month. I am glad to be
introducing this one again this year. Um
so it's important I think uh now more
than ever that we recognize the
celebration of Pride Month. Um I also
appreciate that June has many different
celebrations and uh it you know all have
uh equal time and can be celebrated
together and I think that that's truly
in the spirit of celebrating pride as
well. Um particularly in a year when our
uh trans neighbors are also uh very much
in danger. It's important that we come
out and support this community with this
resolution. So, um, I would make a
motion that we move resolution number 43
to our next meeting of council on June
10th. Second. Motion and a second. Are
there any council comments on the
resolution? Hearing none, all in favor?
I. Any opposed?
Thank you so
much. The next item under the committee
of the whole is uh administration
resolution number 44. Uh this is
authorizing a flag raising to mark Black
History Month in
2026. Um so I always appreciate when
people get out ahead of these things. Uh
we do are required to um to uh approve
these flag raisings and this was
submitted by the NAACP Lancaster branch
uh for uh Junth flag raising and it was
submitted that was last set. Okay. And
so I don't know if I have the date. I
apologize. Let me just click on
that. The old submission that we
changed. And this is submitted to take
place on February 2nd, 2026 with a
backup date of February 3rd,
2026. I would make a motion that we move
this resolution to full counsel on June
10th. Second. A motion and a second.
Councilors, any comments on this one?
Hearing none. All in favor? I I. Any
opposed? Thank you very
much. And related sort of uh
administration resolution number 45
authorizing a flag raising at city hall
to mark Junth in 2026. Again, getting
out ahead of that uh to be prepared for
next year. And I'm just bringing that up
to ensure that I have the right dates.
And this was also submitted by the NAACP
Lancaster branch and they're requesting
to do the flag raising on June 19th,
2026 with a backup date of the 18th in
case uh calling for inclement weather
that day. I would make a motion that we
move this resolution to full counsel on
the 10th. Second. Second. We have a
motion and a second. Counselors, any
comments on the resolution?
Hearing none. All those in favor? I any
opposed?
Thank you. Uh and that will conclude the
committee of the whole. Thank you
everybody. Um we'll now begin the
personnel committee. Uh councelor Claks,
do you have the floor? Thank you
councelor President. The personal
committee has four items on the agenda
for tonight and the first item is the
nomination of Maisa Yoda Bontreger for
appointment to the SH tree commission.
Could you please join us?
Thank you for being here tonight and
thank you for your willingness to serve.
And uh would you please introduce
yourself starting with your name and
block of residence and tell us why you
want to serve on the shed tree
commission? Okay. My name is Marisa
Yoder Bontriger. I live uh I've first
moved to Southand Street in 1988. So
they've been there for a long long time.
Um and I've been involved with tree
planting in that area just about since
1988. Um and it's been neighborhood tree
planting. It's been also in the
northeast.
Um and um yeah, I just I value trees
really highly wherever they are. But I
think in an urban environment,
especially with the city's goals for
water, storm water
reduction, general life quality,
cooling, all those things, I think
they're just a really valuable asset,
and I'd like to do more to support the
city in getting more trees in the
ground, keeping the ones that we have
healthy.
Thank you. Are there any questions from
other members of the committee comments?
Uh thank you Marisa for stepping
forward. I know you bring a lot of
background like you said to to this
issue. Are there things that you feel
like as far as what the city's doing and
getting its both the street trees and
she trees, but also just its overall
tree canopy, things that the city uh
should do better or um what maybe things
that are that are going well? Yeah. Um,
I think that we could do
um change of the traditional approach of
just putting a single sidewalk street
tree in to doing planting strips to
doing um cluster planting in areas where
we're off the sidewalk a little bit. Uh,
and in that way create more habitat and
more storm water reduction. Um, I think
that there could be more coordination
probably between departments. I um I
don't know a lot of the background, but
it seems to me like sometimes sidewalks
are uh put in without maybe consultation
with the the from the from the tree
perspective from the um city arborist
and the urban the urban what are you
called Mike? Forester urban forester.
Um, so I would like to see a very tight
connection between when work is being
done and um, always keeping in mind what
the opportunities might be for adding
tree trees to whatever location.
Thank you.
Uh, are there any other questions or
comments from members of the
committee from council as a whole?
Council please. Thank you Maris Lisa.
Thank you for being here. I just wanted
to make mention are are you a nurse
also? Thank you. I appreciate that. And
thank you for being doing that what you
do and then also being interested in
chia trees. I just leave her neat.
It's kind of lifelong.
Thank you. Thank.
So now I'll make a motion to move uh
this nomination to our next council
meeting on June 10th. Second. All in
favors? I. And uh the personal committee
also has three other nominations for
reappointment to the civil service
board. And those uh individuals
have have been working
on on the commission for on the board
for quite some time and they have uh
expressed their willingness to continue
serving on the board. So
um we have the
nomination of Lloyd Henry for
reappointment to the civil board and the
nomination of Donald Palmer and Tina
Derby to the civil board to the civil
service board. And are there any
questions or comments from members of
the committee regarding those
nominations from council?
I I was going to say the only comment I
would make is I think um might make
sense to move all of these Yeah. at
once.
Okay. So, I'll make a motion to move
those three nominations to our next
council meeting on June 10th. Second.
All in favors? I I I just wanted to add,
if I may, councelor Khalik, that um
we're very fortunate to have Lloyd Henry
because he has a long time, he's a
retired firefighter. Uh Donald Palmer is
a retired uh police chief and um
appreciation for uh Miss Darby who
regularly attends the um civil service
um obstacle course training for our
police officers and has made herself
available um to assist in those efforts.
So I think these are um definitely folks
who have shown a commitment to work.
Thank you mayor for your comment. Great.
Thank you councelor Ber. Thank you very
much, Councelor Kits. Um, I failed to
mention this at the beginning of the
meeting. The next item is the finance
committee and um, I just want to make an
announcement now that resolution 46 that
appears on your agenda is being
withdrawn for this meeting. Um, there's
just like some some timing issues there.
Um, so they will they will reapproach
council with that when the timing is
right. Um, but we're not taking it up.
So therefore, there's no finance
committee meeting this evening. And that
will take us to community planning
committee. Councelor Craig. Thank you,
Council President. Um, the first item on
our on we have two items on the agenda
this evening. The first being the review
of the historical commission
recommendation for 101 South Queen. Is
there anybody from the historical
commission here to address that?
Yes.
Craig, I'm I'm happy to come and speak
for a moment. I also think it's Ryan,
correct? Uh you're representing as a
project architect, too. Okay. So, you
can both just step up real quickly if
you'd like. Great.
Happy to have
I would like to know a little bit about
just a little bit about the project.
Just kind of over. Um my name is Ryan
Griffith. Um I'm the president of
Cornerstone Design Architects. We are
working with Brentwood Builders um who
was our client and the developer for the
property.
Um this was the property was uh it was
it's a historic hotel um but it was a
blighted property. Uh it actually
doesn't have stairs so there's no access
to the third and fourth floor um without
a lift. Um so uh the building uh was
that makes it interesting. It makes it
makes it makes a survey uh something
that I ask my staff to be very careful
with. Um but uh it it is a uh it's a
property that um the
um this is the Swan Hotel. It is the
Swan Hotel. Yeah. Um so it it is a
property that was um the convention
center authority uh put on an RFP. Um
and so um and Brentwood Builders was the
successful uh proposal for that. Um and
so what their proposal is is that
they're uh they're going to adaptively
adaptively reuse it, which is just
converting something to a uh a new use
and bringing back an existing building
into something that can uh continue to
to be uh useful and preserved. Um, and
so the use would be for a 21 uh unit
basically temporary in vacation rental
property. Oh, like a
an Airbnb type thing. Yeah. I don't know
that it's I don't know that it's
technically going to be through that
service or not, but that that idea.
So, um, the idea is that they want to be
able to uh preserve the the corner and
the and the building itself. Uh and then
they would like to be able to uh do uh
it's it's it's here because of a
demolition, right? But the demolition
comp component to this is uh the stairs
that were removed were
nonhistoric, but there's a piece of the
roof basically that's going to be the
existing dormers on Vine Street. So, not
one of our main facing street facing
facades um that will be partially
demolished in order to create uh some
unit space and a and a roof deck um up
on that the Vine Street side of the
street. So, that building is
[Music]
not it's not that big. Correct.
So, how do how how are we going to get
21 units of DV in there?
I think um Rhino, if I might jump in.
I've got a few notes here and if I uh
misstate it, please uh correct me. Um
you're right, councelor Craig. It's not
a particularly large uh property. This
has been one of the challenges for the
redevelopment of the site is uh it is a
significant investment to do the
historic rehabilitation of the building.
But then making the economics work of
the project has been really challenging
which is why it has sit um uh sat vacant
for quite some time. Um this particular
use for the for the site is actually a
really good fit. It's going to be a
boutique hotel but it's a contactless
hotel model. Um and I have in my notes
here that it's a total of 11 units uh
for the building. Is that is that
correct? Yes. Okay. Um
That does make more sense and I
apologize for that. More sense 11 years.
It's bunk beds. I I have a lot of stuff
floating around in my head from
something else. Okay, great. Yes. Uh and
I thought Ryan described very well that
there's just a small portion of the
building that requires uh demolition,
but as a whole uh this historic asset is
being preserved. Uh the historical
commission did recommend approval. Um I
don't believe it was controversial in
any way. That's why we don't have
anybody here from the historical
commission this evening. Um just a
little more context on the site. We had
a zoning interpretation question earlier
in the process. That zoning
interpretation question has been
resolved. Um the project is on a good
track right now and still uh needs to go
uh through land development I believe.
Uh um or some portion of land
development there. Yeah, I think there's
I think that they're still waiting on
land development and then we'll be
working towards uh permit submission.
Yes. Uh building permit submission in
the next month. Great. Are there any
questions from the committee?
So, sorry. Did you say it's just going
to be the units, the 11 units? There's
no commercial or other component. That's
correct. So the the original take on
this or concept was that there would be
nine units and a
small speak easy kind of bar restaurant.
Um
the reality was is that there wasn't a
great way to fit that in and
still get units in there. Um and the
bigger reality and the more important
thing is that there's already plenty of
bars, restaurants, southern markets
across the street. There's plenty of
places to eat and drink in this area of
the city. So, yeah. Um, it's more it's
more like it's more like supporting that
having a place that is not a hotel room
in your most traditional sense to to
stay. Yeah. No, I like the concept and I
I I just know that there was definitely
interest in that, but it what you're
saying makes a lot of sense. Yeah. I
think it would have been a workable and
fun concept, but it would have been
really small scale and probably only
used by the people staying there, right?
This makes a lot of sense. Thank you.
Are there any further questions then?
Okay. Uh thank you, Councelor Craig, and
thank you for being here this evening.
Um my first question is what happens to
that parking lot in the back of the
hotel. The parking lot is uh is I
believe owned by the convention center,
so it will be staying as their property.
I'm not sure what plans they might have
for that. They they use that um service
parking lot for loading in and for um
Yeah. Yes. Yeah. I don't I don't I'm not
aware of any anything that would be
changing that. That was also one of the
um uh challenges to the redevelopment of
this um property was that the convention
center needed to maintain that surface
area parking lot in the back.
And then my my final question is with
you know just 11 units um what are the
what are the rates the nightly rates
going to be in order to get a return
that is uh outside of my pay grade at
this point. Um so I'm not sure what
that's going to look like. Um I'm sure
that there's some kind of um formula
that that they're going to use that it's
hey it needs to compete with Airbnb as a
service. It needs to compete with hotels
as a service. It needs to offer
something a little unique in being um in
a historic building and being
particularly located like it is. I'm not
sure what the rates are going to be. I
would guess I would guess that you could
probably stay at the holiday H holiday
in for less for example, but you're not
going to get a rental home by itself for
something similar in there. So, would
these be like one to twobedroom layouts
with, you know, diet kitchens and living
spaces? Yeah. So, Kitchen at Light is
kind of how it is. And it is it is
really it's someplace where if you could
see yourself maybe visiting Lancaster
for a week, right? And seeing the sites
or being here on business or being here
for a wedding or whatever that might be.
Um that it can be like kind of a
touchdown space for a week, maybe a
little bit more so than a hotel. Um so
that's the idea. and and there's there's
one bedrooms and then there's really
cool loft spaces up on the up on the
upper floor that will have access to
that roof deck that's being created with
part of the demolition. So, um I I think
it'll be I mean I think it's going to be
unique in a lot of ways and and be
offering a little bit of a different
stay experience than a lot of other
places are currently. Thank you. Mhm.
So, the Marriott will be retaining a
parking lot in the back in its entirety.
They will. Yeah. Yeah. convention
center. Yes, they will. Um, so I think
there's a fence there now. Um, there
will be a bit of an addition that's
going off of the back of this which is
going to be an creating an uh space for
an elevator and stairs and a lobby. Uh,
and then the roof deck above the
elevator and stair towers. Um, and so by
the time that gets added onto the back
of the swan, if you'll you can see when
you drive past, there's a little bit of
a there's a gate beyond there, which
that that that uh fence is the property
line. So, it is a small property. Um,
and they'll be they'll be kind of backed
up against a parking lot there.
Are there any further questions from uh
council as a whole?
Just to put a fine point on it, Director
Del, the demolition and construction
that we have before us were both deemed
appropriate and meeting all the
standards for the historical commission.
Is that right? Yes, that's correct. Make
sure we all have that. I'll have seen
that in our memo. So, thank you. Okay.
Thank you so much. Yeah. Um are any
questions from the
public? No. Okay. I'll make a motion to
move this to um full counsel on the 10.
Second. All those in favor? I I Thank
you. Thank you.
Um the next item on our agenda is
resolution number 47 authorizing
submission of the community development
block grant and annual action
plan. And I see Miss Geyser making her
way to the table. Council Craig, if I
could just mention to members of council
the presentation, this was sent to you
just before the meeting. So, you also
have it in your inbox.
Madame Mayor, I think we sent it to you
two ways and for copies. Okay. I have it
for
I love paper. Okay. These will not hold
us. No.
I might have enough. I have more. No,
wait. These are my notes. You have yours
as well. Good.
I just need one. One for county and one
for it's also going to be up on the
I can also share more.
Would you like a paper copy? Oh, they
got one. Great. Thank you.
Teamwork. Thanks to
Okay. Always. All right. Thank you.
Oh, could you councelor Diaz, would you
kindly pass these around? Sure. It's
going to come up later. Well, good
evening, the mayor, counselor,
counselors. Uh, my name is Jen Ruml. I
am the community development
administrator within the department of
planning and economic development and I
manage our community development block
grants funded by the house uh department
of housing and economic I'm sorry the
department of housing and urban
development. I'm pleased to present to
you tonight um our 2025 fiscal year
annual action plan for the utilization
of our 2025 community block development
grant.
Before we get into the allocation
details for this year, we'd like to
present a brief refresher of the
community development block grant
program. The CDBG grant is administered
by HUD and it provides annual grant
entitlements to cities, states, and
Sorry, go ahead. Oh, I'm sorry. I'll
There we go. That's it. I'll try to keep
an eye on both things that are going on.
Um the CDBG program which is
administered by HUD provides entitlement
annual entitlement grants to states,
cities and counties to help develop
viable urban communities by providing
funding and support through the
following. Provision of decent
affordable housing, the creation of a
suitable living environment and the
expansion of economic opportunities
principally to benefit low to moderate
income persons. HUD authorizes CDBG to
be spent on the following eligible
community development activities and
those are listed on the spreadsheet
you're looking right now. Affordable
housing and preservation and production,
public infrastructure improvements,
public services, economic development
and planning and
administration. Is yours wonky? Yeah,
it's all
right. Next slide, please.
Okay. Uh you some of you may remember
this from the caper presentation that we
did back in I believe it was March. Um
I'd like to give you a reminder of some
of the impact that the CDBG program has
had in our the last year of our 5-year
comp plan. So uh some of the information
that we captured in 2024 approximately
20,121 residents were served in 2021. We
estimate that 17,000 of those people
were impacted by the 11 ADA ramps that
were installed in low to moderate income
areas. Uh 364 individuals uh were
documented to have interactions with our
health and housing social worker, Sonia.
422 individuals benefited from
consulting with our two police social
workers. 823 individuals participated in
neighborhood engagement programs. And
that was just of the information we
collected. And
95.8% of those who received assistance
through those that CDBG funding were low
to moderate
income. Next slide,
please. This is just a visual of some of
the partners that we work with and some
of the programs that we fund. So, we've
been lucky enough to work with uh
Tenfold for their H fair housing
program, assets for their community uh
economic development program. SAKa has
been a partner of ours uh in helping to
develop and rehabilitate affordable
housing opportunities. We've also been
able to fund internal programs like I
mentioned before, the police social work
program, the critical repair program,
and the proactive housing code
enforcement program.
um as well as supporting work in the
comprehensive
plan. Next slide, please. This one's
really hard to see and I apologize. Um
just a couple of demographics captured
from our 2024 CDBG
uh expenditures and the people that we
assisted. 35% identified as white, 21%
identified as African-American or black,
37% identified as other or multi-racial,
and 5% declined to provide an answer.
Um, as far as ethnicity goes, 57%
identified as non-Hispanic and 30 43%
identified as Hispanic. Finally, in
2024, CDBG programming supported a
majority of low to moderate income
resident households. 45% or 344 from
those from whom we collected financial
data
um qualified as being extremely low
income.
28% or 215 people identified as being
low income and 22% or 168 people
identified as being moderate income. So,
as you can see, the CDBG program
continues to affect the daily lives of
low to moderate income city residents
daily, and the city continues to monitor
and engage with its community members to
learn and adapt to new and ongoing needs
to serve the city's greatest needs. So,
we expect to see similar results with
the 2025 program and we can't wait to
tell you about what we plan to
do. Next slide,
please. Okay, so on May 15,
2025, the city of Lancaster learned its
anticipated entitlement award amount of
1.14 1.413 $413 million, which
represents a reduction of
2.59% from 2024. Um, we're comfortable
anticipating a program income of
$25,043, which brings our anticipated
total to
1,438,690. That's the amount that we're
using to plan our allocations for 2025.
Unfortunately, the city fell below the
threshold to receive ESG funding again
this year. However, we continue to work
with the Commonwealth to receive
allocations for partners within our own
community. Uh the community development
office is looking forward to using our
2025 allocation to build upon the
success we've achieved over our last
four years of our comm plan. Um as I
mentioned that our comm plan runs from
2021 to 2025. We are now in the fifth
year. Um, the activities we plan to
focus on supporting are strong
neighborhoods, safe places, a
sustainable economy, and sound
government of the mayor's within the
mayor's strategic plan. Um, the comp
plan focus areas that strengthen
neighborhood and housing, expand
economic opportunities and build
communities, and build upon the interim
housing strategy to emphasize, produce,
protect, and sustain affordable housing.
This plan ensures that we are still able
to meet our community development
priorities set out in our 2021 to 2025
consolidated plan and we can continue to
maximize community impact while
minimizing any adverse budgetary impact
to the general
fund. Next slide please.
So, taking a larger look, um, on your
spreadsheets, you can see on the blue
section a complete breakdown of how we
plan to allocate the funds, but here
we're grouping them. So, through our
extensive community engagement efforts
in 2020, we identified four priorities
uh that are HUD eligible goals for our
funding. And our current goals are to
maintain a quality affordable housing,
increase affordable I'm sorry, yes,
increase affordable housing
opportunities, promote neighborhood
quality of life, and expand economic
opportunities. So, in 2025, we're using
the funds uh in this way.
$620,000 we're planning to use to
develop maintain quality, affordable
housing.
$370,000 for public infrastructure
improvements,
$182,000 for public services that
improve the quality of life of our
neighborhoods, $20,000 to expand
economic opportunities, and
$248,000 for planning and
administration. Next slide, please.
Thank you, Bernard.
Despite the fact that the city of
Lancaster has seen a successive annual
reduction in CDBG resources by about 2
to 5% every year since the beginning of
their comm plan uh due to reduction in
census data, the city nonetheless is
tasked with leveraging its funding to
create and foster a viable resilient
community to develop and implement
mutually reinforcing approaches to
providing housing, creating quality
living environments, and expanding
economic ing opportunities for the
primary benefit of low to moderate city
residents and households. Because
2025 is our the fifth year of our 2021
to 2025 consolidated plan. Earlier this
year, the CPED team evaluated its
remaining balances from previous years
of the comp plan and performed a
comprehensive analysis of ongoing and
growing community needs. And as a
result, we brought forth in I believe it
was March a substantial amendment to
city council to reallocate the unspent
fundings to ensure responsible and
timely expenditure of CDBG funds
pursuant to the city's strategic plans
and the overall goals in the comm plan.
As a result, uh the remaining balance of
1.166 million is represented in this
graph. That brings us to our full
funding picture of 2.605.
So, we are we have the ability to we
want to show you what the full picture
is with our carryover and with our new
allocation of what our what we're able
to accomplish this year um with funding.
So, this slide provides a larger picture
of what we're able to accomplish when we
combine our per our I'm sorry, next
slide. We're not I'm sorry. Uh so this
shows us um a better detail of what
we're able to accomplish when we combine
our rollover funds with our new
allocation. We're proposing to allocate
$1.51 million to affordable housing
preservation develop and development
programs including the city's critical
repair program, the proactive housing
code enforcement and affordable housing
development solutions. We just completed
an LOI process to try to help match some
of our uh community partners with best
sources of funding. Um next we will
allocate or we plan to allocate
$445,000 to public infrastructure
improvements by subsidizing street
improvements and community projects in
low to moderate income neighborhoods.
We are also planning to allocate
$193,000 in funding to support public
services which include the health and
housing social worker, the police social
workers, and the T-fold fair housing
program among others. We're planning to
allocate $40,000 to support economic
development activities uh and providing
funding to assets. Just a small note
there, their contract begins on July
1st. So, it's it's technically a a
one-year allocation, but with their
fiscal year beginning July 1st. It's one
year, but it's starting later, so it's
it looks like two fiscal years. Finally,
we are proposing to allocate allocate
$416,000 to program administration and
city planning efforts uh for program
projects such as the East End Small Area
Plan.
Next slide
please. Thank you. So when combined with
the rollover amounts I just wanted to
show you uh that um as the city has told
us and we responded more than half 58%
of the funding is being allocated to
maintain quality affordable housing. 25%
which is a combination of 17% of public
services and 8% of I'm sorry 17% public
facilities and 8% of public services is
being dedicated to promote quality of
life in the neighborhood. 2% is being
allocated to expand economic
opportunities and 14% is being allocated
to planning and administration.
So this funding strategy supports goals
set out in our current con plan despite
a reduction in funding and reflects
overall consistency with the CDBG
framework that we've laid out over the
last five
years. Some additional information about
um individual like the 2025 allocation
and then the how it's combined into the
overall allocation can be found on the
spreadsheet on the second page of the
spreadsheet that I provided. Next slide
please.
If you have not had a chance to look at
the annual action plan, that QR code
will take you directly to it. Um, so,
uh, hard copy is still available at city
hall and you can navigate to it also by
going to the city hall website, clicking
on city government, going down to
community development, and then finding
the draft 2025 annual action plan on our
website. Uh, next slide, please. Here's
a little bit of our timeline. So, we
were pretty proactive. Um, our 2025
annual action plan was posted to our
website April 22nd, 2025. Uh, we have a
required 30 days for posting. So, we uh
put a notice in the newspaper about a
public meeting and about the AAP being
available for view on April 22nd. On
April 20, I'm sorry, May 27th, we more
than 30 days had passed and we held our
public meeting. There was no public
comments received by phone, by mail, or
in person. Our public comment period
closed Wednesday, May 28th. And again,
no public comments were
received. Next slide, please.
Uh just one more reminder that this is
year five of five. Um we wanted to tell
you a little bit more that we're looking
forward to in community development. Um
we are in the early stages of planning
our consolidated planning process for
the 2026 to 2030 cycle. Please stay
tuned for opportunities to provide
feedback on how you can help to inform
CDBG funding and to shape your community
going forward.
Um, with that being said, I would like
to open the floor to questions or
comments you might have at this time.
Are there questions from the committee?
Questions from council as a whole.
Thank you. Um, thank you for the
presentation. Um, I'm always really
interested in in seeing how we do a
little bit more or maintain with less
every year. Um, and obviously the
carryover amount would be really
impactful. How would you say that that
we're impacted was this allocation
impacted by most recent federal budget
cuts and um will our carryover allow us
to maintain particularly in um the
planning and administration? Does that
include the salaries of people who are
funded who are salaries are funded by
this um and will we be able to maintain
them longer to do good work for our
community? So as as of now the reduction
in funding is solely related to a census
change. Um, we were keeping an eye on
announcements regularly to see when they
were announced and they were uh the the
CDBG allocation was announced right
around the time it usually was um this
year and with the amount of funding we
have, we are able to continue to fund
all of the internal positions. Uh I
don't think we've had to make
compromises. Can you comment on that?
Have we had to make compromises? Yeah, I
think from from year to year uh we if we
have had vacancies in one year then that
money would carry forward and as long as
we are administering the programs this
cut was not any greater in fact it's a
little bit less than we were
anticipating. So uh that that helped. So
we are good through the end uh through
the middle of 2026 with this budget for
CDBG and then the budget the recent
budget conversations at the federal
level if there are CDBG cuts would
impact our 2026 allocation which we
would find out about in March I mean
sorry in May next year and then we have
to make some decisions. So, as we go
into the 2026 budget cycle for the city
budget, we we won't know what's
happening overall with the CDBG budget.
Timing is always very difficult. It is.
Yeah. Yeah. That's one thing worth
mentioning. We did plan ahead. So, yeah.
Thank you. That was Thanks for asking
that question. That was what I wanted to
know. I see a question. Thank you. Go
ahead. Thank you, Council Craig. Uh my
question is um do we anticipate any
rollover of funds from 2025 to 2026
especially given that there's a lot of
uncertainty in what funding will look
like further?
Yeah, that's a that's a very good
question. Generally there are funds
remaining. We we have a requirement to
when we get our next year's allocation
or as we're closing out 2025, we're only
allowed to have one and a half times the
allocation remaining. So, they are
requiring us to continue to spend down
the grant. So, we have to be mindful of
that u deadline in November. Uh
simultaneously, we will have money at
the end of 2025 to cover at least the
first six months of 2026. And often in
larger pots of money, for example,
affordable housing development
solutions, if there aren't partners, uh,
ready and able to spend the money, then
we often carry that forward as well. So
staff vacancies and,
um, community needs really drive the the
rollover from one year until the next.
Thank you.
Are there any further questions from
council?
Not really a question, but a comment.
Uh, excellent presentation. Thank you,
Jen. Um, thank you, Rebecca. I, you
know, your team does good work. And I
just want to continue to point out that
like of all the things that the city
could put this money towards, it
continues to put it into housing. And I
just think that that's
noteworthy. We all know that the
affordable housing situation is
difficult out there, but the
city continues to prioritize addressing
it. And I just think that's really
that's a really good thing. So, thank
you so much.
Um, I'll make a motion to move this to
full council and attend. Say again. All
those in favor? I I Thank you. Thank
you. Thank you, ma'am.
That concludes community planning. Thank
you so much. Um, uh, Mr. Paris. Uh, the
last item on the agenda is the clerk's
report confirming that you've submitted
that in writing to all members of
council. He has. Okay. Thank you very
much. Then having reached the end of our
agenda, I will hear a motion to adjurnn.
Motion to adjurnn. Second. Second. All
in favor? I. We'rejourned. Thank you
everybody.